How do you observe something you can't see?
كيف يمكنك مراقبة شيئاً لا يمكنك رؤيته؟
This is the basic question of somebody who's interested
هذا سؤال اساسي لأي شخص مهتم
in finding and studying black holes.
بالبحث عن و دراسة الثقوب السوداء
Because black holes are objects
لان الثقوب السوداء هي أجسام
whose pull of gravity is so intense
ذات قوة جاذبية هائلة
that nothing can escape it, not even light,
بحيث أن لا شيئ يمكنه الهروب منها، بما في ذلك الضوء
so you can't see it directly.
لذلك لا يمكنك رؤيته مباشرة
So, my story today about black holes
لذلك فإن قصتي اليوم عن الثقوب السوداء
is about one particular black hole.
هي عن ثقب أسود محدد
I'm interested in finding whether or not
أنا مهتمة في ايجاد ما إذا كان هناك حقاً
there is a really massive, what we like to call
جسم هائل أم لا، ذلك الذي ندعوه
"supermassive" black hole at the center of our galaxy.
ثقب أسود "فائق الكتلة" في مركز مجرتنا
And the reason this is interesting is that
و السبب بأهمية ذلك أنه
it gives us an opportunity to prove
يعطينا فرصة لاثبات
whether or not these exotic objects really exist.
فيما اذا كانت هذه الاجسام الشاذة موجودة حقاً
And second, it gives us the opportunity
و ثانياً، ذلك يعطينا الفرصة
to understand how these supermassive black holes
لفهم كيف أن هذه الثقوب السوداء الضخمة
interact with their environment,
تتفاعل مع ما يحيطها
and to understand how they affect the formation and evolution
و لفهم كيف يؤثرون في التشكيل و التطور
of the galaxies which they reside in.
للمجرات التي تسكنها
So, to begin with,
لذلك، لنبدأ
we need to understand what a black hole is
نحتاج لفهم ما هو الثقب الأسود
so we can understand the proof of a black hole.
بحيث نستطيع فهم اثبات الثقب الأسود
So, what is a black hole?
لذلك، ما هو الثقب الأسود؟
Well, in many ways a black hole is an incredibly simple object,
حسناً، بطرق عديدة الثقب اأسود هو جسم بسيط بشكل لا يصدق
because there are only three characteristics that you can describe:
لوجود ثلاث خصائص فقط تستطيع أن تصفها:
the mass,
الكتلة
the spin, and the charge.
الدوران، و الشحنة
And I'm going to only talk about the mass.
و سأقوم بالتحدث عن الكتلة فقط
So, in that sense, it's a very simple object.
لذلك و من هذا المفهوم، انه جسم بسيط جداً
But in another sense, it's an incredibly complicated object
و لكن من منطلق آخر، انه جسم معقد جداً
that we need relatively exotic physics to describe,
نحتاج بشكل نسبي لفيزياء شاذة لوصفه
and in some sense represents the breakdown of our physical understanding
و في بعض الاعتبارات انهيار الفيزياء التي نفهمها
of the universe.
عن الكون
But today, the way I want you to understand a black hole,
و لكن اليوم، الطريقة الي أريدكم ان تفهموا لثقب الاسود
for the proof of a black hole,
لاثبات الثقب الاسود
is to think of it as an object
هي بالتفكير به كجسم
whose mass is confined to zero volume.
كتلته محصورة بحجم يساوي الصفر
So, despite the fact that I'm going to talk to you about
لذلك و بغض النظر عن الحقيقة التي سأتحدث معكم عن
an object that's supermassive,
جسم هائل الكتلة
and I'm going to get to what that really means in a moment,
و سأصل لما يعنيه حقيقةً في خلال دقيقة
it has no finite size.
انه لايملك حجم محدد
So, this is a little tricky.
لذلك هذا شيئ مخادع
But fortunately there is a finite size that you can see,
و لكن لحسن الحظ هناك حجم محدد يمكنك رؤيته
and that's known as the Schwarzschild radius.
و هو يدعى بشعاع (قطر) شوارزشيلد
And that's named after the guy who recognized
و سمي بذلك باسم الشخص الذي لاحظ
why it was such an important radius.
لماذا كان هذا الشعاع مهم
This is a virtual radius, not reality; the black hole has no size.
انه شعاع تخيلي و ليس حقيقي، الثقب الاسود لا يملك أبعاد
So why is it so important?
لذا، لما هو مهم لهذه الدرجة؟
It's important because it tells us
انه مهم لأنه يخبرنا
that any object can become a black hole.
بأن كل جسم بإمكانه أن يكون ثقباً أسوداً
That means you, your neighbor, your cellphone,
ذلك يعني أنت، جارك، هاتفك المحمول
the auditorium can become a black hole
المرج يمكن أن تصبحوا ثقباً أسود
if you can figure out how to compress it down
اذا أمكنك اكتشاف كيف تضغطه
to the size of the Schwarzschild radius.
الى حجم شعاع شوارزشيلد
At that point, what's going to happen?
عند تلك النقطة، ما الذي سيحدث؟
At that point gravity wins.
عند تلك النقطة الجاذبية تفوز
Gravity wins over all other known forces.
الجاذبية تفوز على جميع القوى الأخرى المعروفة
And the object is forced to continue to collapse
و يجبر الجسم على الاستمرار بالانهيار
to an infinitely small object.
الى جسم لا متناهي الصغر
And then it's a black hole.
و عندها يكون ثقباً أسودا
So, if I were to compress the Earth down to the size of a sugar cube,
لذلك، اذا ضغطت الكرة الأرضية الى حجم مكعب سكر
it would become a black hole,
ستصبح ثقباً أسوداً
because the size of a sugar cube is its Schwarzschild radius.
لأن حجم مكعب السكر هو شعاع شوارزشيلد
Now, the key here is to figure out what that Schwarzschild radius is.
الآن، المفتاح هنا هو اكتشاف ما هو شعاع شوارزشيلد
And it turns out that it's actually pretty simple to figure out.
و تبين أن ذلك حقيقةً شيئ سهل التحديد للغاية
It depends only on the mass of the object.
انه يعتمد فقط على كتلة الجسم
Bigger objects have bigger Schwarzschild radii.
الاجسام الأكبرلها شعاعات شوارزشيلد أكبر
Smaller objects have smaller Schwarzschild radii.
الاجسام الاصغر لها شعاعات شوارزشيلد أصغر
So, if I were to take the sun
لذا، اذا اخذنا الشمس
and compress it down to the scale of the University of Oxford,
و ضغطناها لحجم جامعة أوكسفورد
it would become a black hole.
ستصبح ثقباً أسوداً
So, now we know what a Schwarzschild radius is.
اذاً نحن نعرف الآن ما هو شعاع شوارزشيلد
And it's actually quite a useful concept,
و هو حقيقةً مفهوم مفيد جداً
because it tells us not only
لأنه لا يخبرنا فقط
when a black hole will form,
متى سيتشكل الثقب الاسود
but it also gives us the key elements for the proof of a black hole.
ولكن سيعطينا المفتاح الأساسي لاثبات الثقب الأسود
I only need two things.
اريد فقط شيئين
I need to understand the mass of the object
اريد أن أفهم كتلة الجسم
I'm claiming is a black hole,
الذي ادعي بكونه ثقباً أسوداً
and what its Schwarzschild radius is.
و ما هو شعاع شوارزشيلد خاصته
And since the mass determines the Schwarzschild radius,
و كون الكتلة تحدد شعاع شوارزشيلد
there is actually only one thing I really need to know.
هنالك شيئ واحد فقط اريد ان أعرفه حقاً
So, my job in convincing you
لذا، عملي من اقناعكم
that there is a black hole
ان هنالك ثقباً أسود
is to show that there is some object
ان أظهر ان هناك جسماً ما
that's confined to within its Schwarzschild radius.
محصور ضمن شعاع شوارزشيلد
And your job today is to be skeptical.
و عملكم اليوم أن تكونوا شكاكين
Okay, so, I'm going to talk about no ordinary black hole;
حسناً، سأتحدث عن الثقب الأسود الاعتيادي
I'm going to talk about supermassive black holes.
سأتحدث عن الثقب الأسود فائق الكتلة
So, I wanted to say a few words about what an ordinary black hole is,
لذا، سأقول بضعة كلمات عن ماهية الثقب الأسود الاعتيلدي
as if there could be such a thing as an ordinary black hole.
كما لو أنه هناك شيئ يدعى ثقب أسود اعتيادي
An ordinary black hole is thought to be the end state
الثقب الاسود الاعتيادي اعتبر على أنه نهاية حالة
of a really massive star's life.
حياة نجم ضخم حقيقي
So, if a star starts its life off
لذلك اذا بدأت حياة نجم بكتلة
with much more mass than the mass of the Sun,
أضخم من كتلة الشمس بالأفول
it's going to end its life by exploding
سينهي حياته بانفجار
and leaving behind these beautiful supernova remnants that we see here.
و يترك خلفه بقايا تلك المستعرات النجمية التي نراها هنا
And inside that supernova remnant
و داخل بقايا تلك المستعرات النجمية
is going to be a little black hole
سيكون هناك ثقبا أسود صغير
that has a mass roughly three times the mass of the Sun.
بكتلة أكبر بقليل من ثلاث أضعاف كتلة الشمس
On an astronomical scale
علي المقياس الفلكي
that's a very small black hole.
ذلك ثقب أسود صغير جداً
Now, what I want to talk about are the supermassive black holes.
و الآن ما أود الحديث عنه هو الثقوب السوداء فائقة الكتلة
And the supermassive black holes are thought to reside at the center of galaxies.
و الثقوب السوداء فائقة الكتلة اعتبرت انها تستوطن مركز المجرات
And this beautiful picture taken with the Hubble Space Telescope
هذه صورة جميلة مأخوذة بواسطة تلسكوب هابل
shows you that galaxies come in all shapes and sizes.
تظهر لكم أن المجرات تأتي بكل الأشكال و الأحجام
There are big ones. There are little ones.
هناك الكبيرة و هناك الصغيرة
Almost every object in that picture there is a galaxy.
و تقريباً كل جسم في تلك الصورة هناك هو مجرة
And there is a very nice spiral up in the upper left.
و هناك لولب جميل جداً في الزاوية العلوية اليسرى
And there are a hundred billion stars in that galaxy,
و هناك مائة بليون نجم في تلك المجرة
just to give you a sense of scale.
فقط لاعطيكم الاحساس بالحجم
And all the light that we see from a typical galaxy,
و كل الضوء الذي ترونه من مجرة تقليدية
which is the kind of galaxies that we're seeing here,
مثل المجرات التي نرى هنا
comes from the light from the stars.
يأتي من ضوء النجوم
So, we see the galaxy because of the star light.
لذلك نرى المجرة بسبب ضوء النجوم
Now, there are a few relatively exotic galaxies.
الآن هناك قليل من المجرات الشاذة بشكل نسبي
I like to call these the prima donna of the galaxy world,
احب ان اسميهم السيدة الاولى في عالم المجرات
because they are kind of show offs.
لأنهم نوعاً ما يستعرضون
And we call them active galactic nuclei.
و ندعوهم نوى المجرات النشطة
And we call them that because their nucleus,
و ندعوهم كذلك بسبب نواتهم
or their center, are very active.
أو مركزهم كونه ناشط جداً
So, at the center there, that's actually where
لذلك، عند المركز، هناك حقاً
most of the starlight comes out from.
يأتي منه معظم ضوء النجوم
And yet, what we actually see is light
و للآن ما تراه فعلاً هو ضوء
that can't be explained by the starlight.
لا يمكن وصفه بضوء النجوم
It's way more energetic.
انه عالي الطاقة بطبيعته
In fact, in a few examples it's like the ones that we're seeing here.
في الحقيقة، بأمثلة قليلة انه يشبه ما نراه هنا
There are also jets emanating out from the center.
و هناك أيضاً دفقات تنبعث من المركز
Again, a source of energy that's very difficult to explain
ثانيةً، مصدر طاقة عصي عن التفسير
if you just think that galaxies are composed of stars.
اذا كنت تظن ان المجرات مؤلفة من نجوم
So, what people have thought is that perhaps
لذلك ما فكر فيه الناس انه ربما
there are supermassive black holes
هناك ثقوب سوداء فائقة الكتلة
which matter is falling on to.
بحيث تسقط المادة فيها
So, you can't see the black hole itself,
لذلك لا يمكنك رؤية الثقب الاسود نفسه
but you can convert the gravitational energy of the black hole
ولكن يمكن ان تحول الطاقة الجاذبة للثقب الاسود
into the light we see.
لضوء يمكنك رؤيته
So, there is the thought that maybe supermassive black holes
لذلك هناك اعتقاد انه ربما الثقوب السوداء فائقة الكتلة
exist at the center of galaxies.
تتواجد بمراكز المجرات
But it's a kind of indirect argument.
و لكن ذلك نوع من المجادلة الغير مباشرة
Nonetheless, it's given rise to the notion
ومع هذا، انه يعطي دفعة لنظرية
that maybe it's not just these prima donnas
انه لربما ليس فقط السيدات الأول تلك
that have these supermassive black holes,
التي تملك ثقوب سوداء فائقة الكتلة
but rather all galaxies might harbor these
و لكن كل المجرات لربما تستضيف تلك
supermassive black holes at their centers.
الثقوب السوداء الفائقة في مراكزها
And if that's the case -- and this is an example of a normal galaxy;
و اذا كانت تلك هي القضية -- و هذا مثال عن مجرة عادية
what we see is the star light.
ما نراه هو ضوء النجوم
And if there is a supermassive black hole,
و اذا كان هناك ثقب أسود فائق الكتلة
what we need to assume is that it's a black hole on a diet.
ما نريد افتراضه انه ثقب اسود في حالة حمبة
Because that is the way to suppress the energetic phenomena that we see
لأن تلك هي الطريقة لاخماد ظاهرة الطاقة التي نرى
in active galactic nuclei.
في نواة المجرة النشطة
If we're going to look for these stealth black holes
اذا كنا سنبحث عن تلك الثقوب السوداء الشبح
at the center of galaxies,
في مركز المجرات
the best place to look is in our own galaxy, our Milky Way.
المكان الأفضل للبحث هو في مجرتنا، درب التبانة
And this is a wide field picture
و هذه صورة عريضة
taken of the center of the Milky Way.
مأخوذة لمركز درب التبانة
And what we see is a line of stars.
و ما نراه هو خط النجوم
And that is because we live in a galaxy which has
وهذا بسبب ان المجرة التي نعيش فيها
a flattened, disk-like structure.
مسطحة على شكل قرص
And we live in the middle of it, so when we look towards the center,
و نعيش في منتصفها، لذلك عندما ننظر للمركز
we see this plane which defines the plane of the galaxy,
نرى منبسط يبين انبساط مجرتنا
or line that defines the plane of the galaxy.
او خط يحدد انبساط مجرتنا
Now, the advantage of studying our own galaxy
الآن، الميزة من دراسة مجرتنا
is it's simply the closest example of the center of a galaxy
ببساطة هي انها المثال الأقرب لمركز مجرة
that we're ever going to have, because the next closest galaxy
يمكن لنا الحصول عليها أبداً، لأن المجرة التالية الاقرب
is 100 times further away.
هي١٠٠ مرة أبعد
So, we can see far more detail in our galaxy
لذلك يمكن رؤية تفاصيل أكثر في مجرتنا
than anyplace else.
عن أي مكان آخر
And as you'll see in a moment, the ability to see detail
و كما سترون في دقيقة، قابلية رؤية التفاصيل
is key to this experiment.
هو المفتاح لهذه التجربة
So, how do astronomers prove that there is a lot of mass
لذا، كيف يثبت علماء الفضاء أن هناك كثير من الكتلة
inside a small volume?
في داخل حيز صغير؟
Which is the job that I have to show you today.
حيث أنه العمل الذي ينبغي أن أريه اليوم
And the tool that we use is to watch the way
و الأداة التي نستخدمها هي مراقبة طريقة
stars orbit the black hole.
دوران النجوم في مدار الثقب الأسود
Stars will orbit the black hole
ستدور النجوم في مسار الثقب الأسود
in the very same way that planets orbit the sun.
بنفس الطريقة التي تدور الكواكب حول الشمس
It's the gravitational pull
انها القوة الجاذبة
that makes these things orbit.
التي تجعل الأشياء تشكل مدارات.
If there were no massive objects these things would go flying off,
اذا لم يكن هناك أجسام ضخمة ستذهب هذه الاجسام مبتعدة
or at least go at a much slower rate
أو على الأقل ستسير بمعدل أبطأ بكثير
because all that determines how they go around
لأن ما يحدد دورانهم
is how much mass is inside its orbit.
هو كمية الكتلة الموجودة في مدارهم
So, this is great, because remember my job is to show
لذلك، هذا رائع، لأن عملي اذا تذكرت هو لأري
there is a lot of mass inside a small volume.
أن هناك الكثير من المادة في حيز صغير
So, if I know how fast it goes around, I know the mass.
لذا، كنت أعرف سرعة الدوران، فسأعرف الكتلة
And if I know the scale of the orbit I know the radius.
و إذا عرفت مقياس المدار فسأعرف قطره
So, I want to see the stars
لذا، اريد رؤية النجوم
that are as close to the center of the galaxy as possible.
القريبة من مركز المجرة بقدر الامكان
Because I want to show there is a mass inside as small a region as possible.
لأني اريد أن أري الكتلة داخل منطقة صغيرة قدر الامكان
So, this means that I want to see a lot of detail.
لذلك، هذا يعني أن أرى الكثير من التفاصيل
And that's the reason that for this experiment we've used
و هذا هو سبب استخدامنا لهذه التجربة
the world's largest telescope.
أكبر منظار في العالم
This is the Keck observatory. It hosts two telescopes
انه مرصد كيك. الذي يأوي منظارين
with a mirror 10 meters, which is roughly
بمرآة قطرها ١٠ أمتار، الذي تقريباً
the diameter of a tennis court.
أبعاد حلبة التنس
Now, this is wonderful,
الآن، هذا رائع
because the campaign promise
لأن الحملة بالتلسكوبات الكبيرة
of large telescopes is that is that the bigger the telescope,
تعد بأن كلما كبر المنظار،
the smaller the detail that we can see.
كلما أمكننا رؤية تفاصل أدق
But it turns out these telescopes, or any telescope on the ground
لكن وجدنا أن هذه التلسكوبات، أو أي تلسكوب على الأرض
has had a little bit of a challenge living up to this campaign promise.
لديه تحدي صغير لاضطلاع بهذا الوعد
And that is because of the atmosphere.
و هو بسبب الغلاف الجوي
Atmosphere is great for us; it allows us
الغلاف الجوي عظيم لنا، أنه يمكنّنا
to survive here on Earth.
من النجاة على سطح الأرض
But it's relatively challenging for astronomers
و لكنه يشكل تحدياً نسبياً للفلكيين
who want to look through the atmosphere to astronomical sources.
الذين يودون النظر عبر الجو للمصادر الفلكية
So, to give you a sense of what this is like,
لذا، لاعطائكم معنى ذلك بشكل حسي
it's actually like looking at a pebble
انه كالنظر لحصاة
at the bottom of a stream.
في قاع جدول
Looking at the pebble on the bottom of the stream,
النظر لحصاة في قاع جدول،
the stream is continuously moving and turbulent,
و الجدول يتحرك و يموج بشكل دائم،
and that makes it very difficult to see the pebble on the bottom of the stream.
و هذا يجعل من الصعب جداً رؤية الحصاة في القاع
Very much in the same way, it's very difficult
و بشكل مشابه جداً بنفس الطريقة، انه لمن الصعب جداً
to see astronomical sources, because of the
رؤية المصادر الفلكية، بسبب
atmosphere that's continuously moving by.
الغلاف الجوي الذي يترك بشكل دائم
So, I've spent a lot of my career working on ways
لذا، قضيت الكثير في مهنتي في العمل على طرق
to correct for the atmosphere, to give us a cleaner view.
لتصحيح الجو، ليعطينا منظراً أوضح
And that buys us about a factor of 20.
و هذا يعطينا تقريباً معامل بحدود ٢٠
And I think all of you can agree that if you can
و أظن أن كل ما يمكنكم الموافقة عليه أنه إذا كان بإمكاننا
figure out how to improve life by a factor of 20,
ايجاد كيف يمكن تحسين الحياة بمعامل ٢٠
you've probably improved your lifestyle by a lot,
لربما طورنا نمط حياتنا بشكل كبير
say your salary, you'd notice, or your kids, you'd notice.
لنقل راتبك، يمكنك ملاحظته، أو أولادك
And this animation here shows you one example of
و هذا الفلم يريكم مثال عن
the techniques that we use, called adaptive optics.
التقنيات المستخدمة، المدعوة البصريات المتكيفة
You're seeing an animation that goes between
انكم تشاهدون فلماً يدور حول
an example of what you would see if you don't use this technique --
مثال عما سترونه اذا لم تستخدم تلك التقنيات
in other words, just a picture that shows the stars --
بكلمات أخرى، صورة ترينا النجوم
and the box is centered on the center of the galaxy,
و الصندوق متمركز في مركز المجرة
where we think the black hole is.
حيث نعتقد بوجود الثقب الأسود
So, without this technology you can't see the stars.
لذلك، بدون هذه التقنية لايمكننا رؤية النجوم
With this technology all of a sudden you can see it.
و بهذه التقنية فجأة اصبحت تراها
This technology works by introducing a mirror
تلك التقنية تعمل بعرض مرآة
into the telescope optics system
في نظام التلسكوب البصري
that's continuously changing to counteract what the atmosphere is doing to you.
ذلك يعدل بشكل دائم لمواجهة ما يعمله الجو لك
So, it's kind of like very fancy eyeglasses for your telescope.
لذا، انها تشبه نظارات جميله لمنظارك
Now, in the next few slides I'm just going to focus on
الآن، في الشرائح القادمة، سأقوم فقط بالتركيز على
that little square there.
المربع الصغير هناك
So, we're only going to look at the stars inside that small square,
لذلك سنقوم بالنظر الى النجوم في ذلك المربع الصغير فقط
although we've looked at all of them.
على الرغم من اننا نظرنا اليهم جميعاً
So, I want to see how these things have moved.
لذا أود رؤية كيف تحركت تلك الأشياء
And over the course of this experiment, these stars
و خلال مدة هذه التجربة تحركت
have moved a tremendous amount.
هذه النجوم بمقدار هائل
So, we've been doing this experiment for 15 years,
و كنا نقوم بهذه التجربة لـ ١٥ عام
and we see the stars go all the way around.
و نرى النجوم تسير بكل الاتجاهات
Now, most astronomers have a favorite star,
و الآن معظم الفلكيين لديهم نجمهم المفضل
and mine today is a star that's labeled up there, SO-2.
و نجمي اليوم هو المسمى هناك، SO-2
Absolutely my favorite star in the world.
بهو بشكل مطلق نجمي المفضل في العالم
And that's because it goes around in only 15 years.
و ذلك لأنه يدور هناك فقط في١٥ عاماً
And to give you a sense of how short that is,
و لجعلكم تحسون كم ذلك قصير
the sun takes 200 million years to go around the center of the galaxy.
تأخذ الشمس ٢٠٠ مليون سنة لتدور حول مركز المجرة
Stars that we knew about before, that were as close to the center of the galaxy
و النجوم التي عرفناها من قبل القريبة من مركز المجرة بقدر الامكان
as possible, take 500 years.
تستغرق ٥٠٠ سنة
And this one, this one goes around in a human lifetime.
و هذا النجم، يدور في غضون حياة المرء
That's kind of profound, in a way.
ذلك عميق بشكل
But it's the key to this experiment. The orbit tells me
و لكنه المفتاح لتلك التجربة. يخبرني المدار
how much mass is inside a very small radius.
كم من الكتلة داخل القطر الصغير جداً
So, next we see a picture here that shows you
لذا نرى لاحقاً هنا الصورة التي اريكم
before this experiment the size to which we could
قبل هذه التجربة حجم ما يحجز
confine the mass of the center of the galaxy.
كتلة مركز المجرة
What we knew before is that there was four million
ما نعلمه سابقاً انه كان اربعة ملايين مرة
times the mass of the sun inside that circle.
أكبر من كتلة الشمس في داخل تلك الدائرة
And as you can see, there was a lot of other stuff inside that circle.
و كما ترون، هناك الكثير من الاشياء الاخرى داخل الدائرة
You can see a lot of stars.
يمكنك رؤية العديد من النجوم
So, there was actually lots of alternatives
لذا كان هناك الكثير من البدائل
to the idea that there was a supermassive black hole at the center of the galaxy,
لفكرة كون هنالك ثقب أسود بالغ الكتلة في مركز المجرة
because you could put a lot of stuff in there.
لأنه يمكنكم وضع الكثير من الأشياء هناك
But with this experiment, we've confined
ولكن في هذه التجربة حصرنا
that same mass to a much smaller volume
هذه الكتلة الضخمة في حجم أصغر
that's 10,000 times smaller.
10 آلاف مرة أصغر
And because of that, we've been able to show
و بسبب ذلك، كنا قادرين أن نري
that there is a supermassive black hole there.
أن هناك ثقب أسود بالغ الكتلة
To give you a sense of how small that size is,
لاعطائكم فكرة عن صغر حجمه
that's the size of our solar system.
انه حجم نظامنا الشمسي
So, we're cramming four million times the mass of the sun
لذلك نحن نتكلم عن أربعة ملايين مرة حجم الشمس
into that small volume.
في ذلك الحجم الصغير
Now, truth in advertising. Right?
الآن الحقيقة في الاعلان اليس كذلك؟
I have told you my job is to get it down to the Schwarzchild radius.
اخبرتكم ان عملي ان اصغره لحجم شعاع شوارزشيلدز
And the truth is, I'm not quite there.
و الحقيقة انني لست هناك تماماً
But we actually have no alternative today
و لكن ليس لدينا بديل اليوم
to explaining this concentration of mass.
لنشرح ذلك التركيز في الكتلة
And, in fact, it's the best evidence we have to date
و في الحقيقة، انه الدليل الأفضل لدينا لليوم
for not only existence of a supermassive black hole
في انه ليس وجود ثقب أسود بالغ الكتلة
at the center of our own galaxy, but any in our universe.
في مركز مجرتنا، بل في كامل كوننا
So, what next? I actually think
لذا ما التالي؟ أنا أظن حقيقة
this is about as good as we're going to do with today's technology,
انه جيد بقدر ما نعمله بتقنيتنا الحالية
so let's move on with the problem.
لذلك لنكمل في مسألتنا
So, what I want to tell you, very briefly,
لذا ما سأقوله لكم بشكل مختصر
is a few examples
هو بضع أمثلة
of the excitement of what we can do today
عن الإثارة بما يمكننا عمله اليوم
at the center of the galaxy, now that we know that there is,
في مركز المجرة، نعرف الآن أن هنالك
or at least we believe,
أو على الأقل نحن نعتقد
that there is a supermassive black hole there.
أن هنالك ثقب أسود هائل هناك
And the fun phase of this experiment
و الجزء الممتع في هذه التجربة
is, while we've tested some of our ideas
هو أنه بينما كنا نقوم بامتحان أفكارنا
about the consequences of a supermassive black hole
حول نتائج الثقب الأسود العملاق
being at the center of our galaxy,
الموجود في مركز مجرتنا
almost every single one
تقريباً كل واحد
has been inconsistent with what we actually see.
كان متناقضاً مع ما نراه حقاً
And that's the fun.
و هذا هو الممتع.
So, let me give you the two examples.
لذلك، دعوني اعطيكم مثالين
You can ask, "What do you expect
يمكنكم السؤال، " ماذا تتوقعون
for the old stars, stars that have been around the center of the galaxy
للنجوم المعمرة، النجوم التي كانت حول مركز المجرة
for a long time, they've had plenty of time to interact with the black hole."
لمدة طويلة، كان لديهم الوقت الكافي لتتفاعل مع الثقب الأسود
What you expect there is that old stars
ما تتوقعه هناك تلك النجوم المعمرة
should be very clustered around the black hole.
متجمعة بشكل كبير حول الثقب الأسود
You should see a lot of old stars next to that black hole.
ينبغي أن ترى الكثير من النجوم بقرب الثقب الأسود
Likewise, for the young stars, or in contrast, the young stars,
علـى نفس النمط، للنجوم الشابة، أو بشكل تبايني
they just should not be there.
لا يجب أن تكون هناك
A black hole does not make a kind neighbor to a stellar nursery.
الثقب الأسود لا يشكل جاراً طيباً لحضانة النجوم
To get a star to form, you need a big ball of gas and dust to collapse.
لتشكيل النجم، يلزمك كرة كبيرة من الغاز و الغبار لتنهار.
And it's a very fragile entity.
و هو كيان هش جداً
And what does the big black hole do?
و ماذا يفعل الثقب الأسود؟
It strips that gas cloud apart.
انه يشرّح سحابة الغاز لأجزاء
It pulls much stronger on one side than the other
انه يسحب من جانب بشكل أكبر من الآخر
and the cloud is stripped apart.
و السحابة تتفتت لأجزاء
In fact, we anticipated that star formation shouldn't proceed in that environment.
في الحقيقة، نحن توقعنا أن تشكيل النجوم لايجب أن يستمر في هذه البيئة
So, you shouldn't see young stars.
لذا، لايجب رؤية النجوم الشابة
So, what do we see?
لذا، ما الذي نراه؟
Using observations that are not the ones I've shown you today,
باستخدام مراقب غير التي رأيناها اليوم،
we can actually figure out which ones are old and which ones are young.
يمكننا حقاً معرفة أيها الجديدة و أيها المعمرة.
The old ones are red.
المعمرة هي الحمراء
The young ones are blue. And the yellow ones, we don't know yet.
و الشابة هي الزرقاء. و الصفراء لا نعرف للآن ما هي.
So, you can already see the surprise.
لذلك، يمكنك رؤية مفاجأة
There is a dearth of old stars.
هناك ندرة بالنجوم المعمرة.
There is an abundance of young stars, so it's the exact opposite of the prediction.
هناك كثرة من النجوم الشابة، و هو عكس ما كان متوقع
So, this is the fun part.
و هذا هو الجزء الممتع
And in fact, today, this is what we're trying to figure out,
و في الحقيقة، اليوم هذا ما نحاول أن ندركه
this mystery of how do you get --
ذلك الغموض حول كيفية الحصول--
how do you resolve this contradiction.
كيف يمكنك حل هذا التناقض
So, in fact, my graduate students
لذا طلابي المتخرجون
are, at this very moment, today, at the telescope,
موجودون الآن و في هذه الحظة عند المنظار
in Hawaii, making observations to get us
في هاواي، يقومون بالمراقبة لايصالنا
hopefully to the next stage,
للمرحلة المقبلة
where we can address this question
حيث يمكننا بحث هذا السؤال
of why are there so many young stars,
حول لماذا هناك العديد من النجوم الشابة،
and so few old stars.
و القليل من النجوم المعمرة
To make further progress we really need to look at the orbits
لتحقيق تقدم أكبر نحتاج حقاً للنظر
of stars that are much further away.
الى مدارات النجوم الأبعد
To do that we'll probably need much more
لنقوم بذلك نحتاج على الأرجح تقنية
sophisticated technology than we have today.
أكثر تعقيداً من التي لدينا اليوم
Because, in truth, while I said we're correcting
لأنه، في الحقيقة، بينما أقول كنا نصحح
for the Earth's atmosphere, we actually only
تأثيرات الغلاف الجوي، فنحن بالحقيقة نصحح فقط
correct for half the errors that are introduced.
نصف الأخطاء الناتجة
We do this by shooting a laser up into the atmosphere,
نقوم بذلك بإطلاق ليزر الى الغلاف الجوي،
and what we think we can do is if we
و ما نظن أننا نفعله اننا
shine a few more that we can correct the rest.
اذا قمنا بزيادة اللمعان قليلاً سنصحح الباقي
So this is what we hope to do in the next few years.
و هذا ما نأمل بفعله في السنوات القليلة القادمة
And on a much longer time scale,
و بمقياس زمني أكبر،
what we hope to do is build even larger telescopes,
ما نأمل بفعله هو بناء مناظير أكبر،
because, remember, bigger is better in astronomy.
لأنه، اذا تتذكرون، كلما كان أكبر كلما كان أفضل في علم الفلك
So, we want to build a 30 meter telescope.
لذا، نريد بناء منظار طوله 30 متر
And with this telescope we should be able to see
و بهذا المنظار يجب أن نكون قادرين على رؤية
stars that are even closer to the center of the galaxy.
النجوم التي هي أقرب من مركز المجرة.
And we hope to be able to test some of
و نأمل أن نكون قادرين على اختبار بعض من
Einstein's theories of general relativity,
نظرية اينشتاين حول النسبية العامة
some ideas in cosmology about how galaxies form.
بعض الأفكار في علم الكون حول كيفية تشكل المجرات
So, we think the future of this experiment
لذا، نظن أن مستقبل هذه التجربة
is quite exciting.
مثير حقاً
So, in conclusion, I'm going to show you an animation
لذا، و كنتيجة، سأريكم فيلم
that basically shows you how these
يري بشكل أساسي كيف
orbits have been moving, in three dimensions.
هذه المدارات تتحرك، في ثلاث أبعاد.
And I hope, if nothing else,
و آمل، ان لم يكن شيئ آخر،
I've convinced you that, one, we do in fact
أن أكون قد أقنعتكم أولاً، آننا فعلاً
have a supermassive black hole at the center of the galaxy.
لدينا ثقب أسود عملاق في مركز المجرة.
And this means that these things do exist in our universe,
و هذا يعني أن هذه الأشياء موجودة في كوننا
and we have to contend with this, we have to explain
و نحن راضين بهذا، يجب علينا أن نشرح
how you can get these objects in our physical world.
كيف يمكننا الحصول على هذه الأجسام في عالمنا الواقعي.
Second, we've been able to look at that interaction
ثانياً، أمكننا النظر لذلك التفاعل
of how supermassive black holes interact,
حول كيفية تفاعل الثقوب السوداء العملاقة،
and understand, maybe, the role in which they play
و ربما فهم، الدور الذي تلعبه
in shaping what galaxies are, and how they work.
بتشكيل المجرات بشكاها الحالي، و كيف تعمل
And last but not least,
و أخيراً، و ليس آخراً
none of this would have happened
لا شيئ من ذلك سيحدث
without the advent of the tremendous progress
بدون حلول التقدم الهائل
that's been made on the technology front.
الذي حدث على صعيد التقنية
And we think that this is a field that is moving incredibly fast,
و نعتقد انه المجال الذي يتقدم بسرعة لا تصدق
and holds a lot in store for the future.
و يخبئ الكثير في جعبته للمستقبل
Thanks very much.
شكرا جزيلاً
(Applause)
(تصفيق)